原视频名：Nauka & New Shepard Fly To Space - What Do They Have In Common
原作者名：Scott Manley
视频来源：youtu.be/CtSmFsPbT-g
原视频发布日期：20210721
字幕翻译：旋火
Hello it's Scott Manley here.
你好 我是Scott Manley
This morning we woke up to the launch of Nauka on its way to the International Space Station.
今天早上 我们被科学号的发射所惊醒 它正在前往国际空间站的路上
This is a launch which has been long delayed
这是一次已经被长期推迟的发射
and it's in fact one of four long delayed launches to space that are happening in July.
事实上 它是7月份进行的四次长期推迟的太空发射之一
This module was originally built over 20 years ago.
这个模块最初是在20多年前建造的
It was originally a backup for Zarya which is the core of the International Space Station.
它最初是作为国际空间站的核心 曙光号的备份
That was so critical that if that was to fail they had this ready to go as a backup.
它是如此重要 以至于如果它发生故障 他们准备好了科学号作为备份
It's based on the FGB, Functional Cargo Block design
它是基于FGB功能货舱设计的
which was originally actually supposed to be a cargo ship that would carry stuff to the Almaz Space Stations.
FGB最初实际上应该是一艘货运飞船 将物资运到金刚石空间站
But it didn't really fly more than a couple of times as a test for the cargo version
但作为货运飞船的测试 它并没有真正飞过几次
but it did get used as a framework for building modules for Mir and the International Space Station
但它确实被用作为和平号和国际空间站模块建造的框架
and after Zarya launched perfectly
而在曙光号的完美发射之后
they had an extra space station module sitting around ready to be converted.
这个额外的空间站模块就在等待 准备进行改造
So in 2005 Roscosmos created Nauka which is a modification of the original design.
所以在2005年 俄罗斯航天局创造了科学号 这是对原始设计的修改
They added a European Robot Arm.
他们增加了一个欧洲机械臂
They switched out a lot of the hardware inside and refilled it with much more experiments.
他们换掉了里面的很多设备 增加了更多的实验设备
And that's what's launching today.
这就是今天发射的东西
Why did it take so long?
为什么要花这么长时间？
Well 2007 was the original launch date
恩 2007年是最初的发射日期
and that inevitably got pushed backwards.
而这不可避免地被推后了
And then they started to find fuel leaks.
然后他们开始发现燃料泄漏
They failed during testing
燃料系统未能通过测试
and the propellant that is on this is the nasty corrosive hypergolic stuff.
而这上面的推进剂是讨厌的腐蚀性的自燃推进剂
They just kept on finding problems with that fuel system.
他们只是不断发现燃料系统的问题
First they had leaks that damaged stuff.
首先是存在泄漏 有设备损坏
Then they found that there were metal shavings getting into propellant lines.
然后他们发现有金属屑进入推进剂管道
They found shavings in the tanks.
同时在储罐中发现了金属屑
And when they wanted to just replace the tanks they found that tanks were no longer made
当他们想更换储罐的时候 发现储罐已经不再生产了
because this is a design dating from the 1970s.
因为这是一个可以追溯到20世纪70年代的设计
Yeah this has just been a huge odyssey.
是的 这一直是一个艰难的过程
Earlier this month they covered it in the thermal insulation blankets
本月早些时候 科学号盖上了隔热毯
encapsulated in the Proton fairing
封装在质子火箭的整流罩中
and they released a bunch of publicity photos
之后 他们发布了一系列的宣传照片
whereupon somebody familiar with the project pointed out that
这时 有熟悉该项目的人指出
some of the critical sensors that were supposed to be covered by thermal blankets weren't
一些应该被隔热毯覆盖的关键传感器没有被覆盖住
so they had to take it out of the fairing and cut up new blankets and cover those objects
所以他们不得不把它从整流罩中取出来 切出新的隔热毯来覆盖这部分
so that pushed the date back until finally today
因此 发射日期被推迟到今天
and it worked just fine.
而发射很成功
The Proton rocket is ugly.
(虽然)质子号火箭很难看
It is old.
它很老
自2016年起的16次质子-M火箭发射均成功，来源en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_Proton_launches
But you know it is actually reliable
但你知道它实际上是可靠的
when you get that much amount of angry chemicals the stuff can't fail to burn.
当你得到那么多愤怒的化学物质时 这些东西不可能不燃烧
The trick is just making sure that it burns through the rocket nozzles rather than you know anything else.
诀窍只是确保它通过火箭的喷嘴燃烧 而不是你知道的其他东西
The Proton is a three-stage rocket that is roughly comparable in performance to that of the Falcon 9.
质子号是一个三级火箭 在性能上与猎鹰9号大致相当
猎鹰9号高70米，质子-M高53米，
来源en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Falcon_9，en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Proton_(rocket_family)
It's obviously a bit shorter.
显然它要短一些
It uses highly toxic propellant in the form of UDMH and nitrogen tetroxide.
它使用高毒性的推进剂 具体来说是偏二甲肼和四氧化二氮
Has three stages.
三个分级具体来说
The first stage in the second stage use hot staging.
一二级使用热分离
That's where you basically light the engines on the second stage before the first stage is separated
基本上来说就是在一级分离前点燃二级的发动机
And the whole point here is that it means you
这就意味着
don't have to worry about propellant settling when you drop the stages.
在分级时 你不必担心推进剂的沉底
One of the problems that can happen if you don't have this
如果你没有这样做 可能发生的一个问题是
is as soon as you separate the stage and let the other one cruise
一旦你分离了这一级 同时让另一级滑行
then the aerodynamic drag pushes the fuel to the front of the tank
那么空气阻力就会把燃料推到储罐的前面
and suddenly you have gas bubbles in your propellant
然后你的推进剂中突然出现了气泡
which is not good for engines that you don't want to explode.
这对你不希望爆炸的发动机来说不是好事
The second to third stage separation isn't quite as rough as this.
二级到三级的分离并不像这样粗暴
They have these four little vernier engines that need for roll and gimbal control.
三级上的四个小游机 用于滚转和矢量控制
二三级分离仍然是热分离，但是不需要使用杆系结构的级间段
And you see them lighting up here pushing the stages apart
这里你可以看到三级游机的点火 将分级推离
and then the core engine lights up.
之后芯发动机点火
So yeah the launch basically went off according to schedule
所以 是的 发射基本上是按计划进行的
which is fantastic considering the troubled history of the module itself.
考虑到该模块本身的麻烦历史 这真是太棒了
I guess they've had a lot more practice with Proton than they have with space station modules.
我猜他们在质子号发射上的训练比在空间站模块上的多得多
Seriously though it's great.
不过说真的 这很好
This is up in space now.
现在科学号已经在太空了
It will have to undergo some tests to make sure that is able to fly and navigate in orbit.
它得接受一些测试 以确保能够在轨道上飞行和导航
Once that's confirmed it will start making its way to the space station
一旦确认 其将开始前往空间站
but before it can dock they have to undock the Pirs module
但在能够停靠之前 必须分离码头号模块 让出其对接口
which has been used as an air lock for the last 20 years.
而码头号模块在过去20年中一直被用作气闸舱
That will undock and return to earth
它将分离并返回地球
and then this will autonomously dock onto the space station
然后科学号将与空间站自主对接
and we'll be really happy to have more space on the space station.
而我们将非常高兴地看到空间站拥有了更多的空间
So yeah this has been waiting over 20 years to fly to space
那么 是的 科学号已经等了20多年才飞到太空
but that's nothing compared to Wally Funk.
但与沃利·冯克相比 这算不了什么
So yeah mainstream news was covering Blue Origin's New Shepard flight yesterday.
那么 是的 主流新闻昨天正在报道蓝色起源的新谢泼德飞行
Obviously they were all talking about billionaire Jeff Bezos going to space
显然 他们都在谈论亿万富翁杰夫·贝佐斯上太空的事
but most space people were more interested in the fact that Wally got to fly.
但大多数太空人更感兴趣的是沃利能够飞行的事实
I mean she was easily the most qualified individual on the crew
我的意思是 她肯定是乘员中最有资格的人
youtu.be/0b1VgtyIQN0
and as I've said has more flight hours than any astronaut currently in space.
而且正如我之前所说 她的(航空)飞行时间比目前在太空中的任何宇航员都要多
And her enthusiasm showed when she was the first person to climb up those stairs
在她第一个爬上这些楼梯时 表现出了(极大的)热情
which you know again 82 years old.
你知道她已经82岁了
There's a lot of people that won't be able to do this.
有很多人(在这个岁数)无法做到这一点
There's a lot of people that are much younger that won't fit the qualifications
(甚至)有很多年轻的人不符合资格
because they're too heavy,
因为他们太重
the wrong size or they can't handle these stairs
(身高)不合适 或者他们不能应付这些楼梯
which is part of the requirement.
而这些也是要求的一部分
What's also interesting on this flight is we had the youngest person to fly in space.
这次飞行的另一个有趣之处在于 创造了进入太空最年轻者的记录
That kid in the back Oliver from uh the Netherlands.
后面的那个孩子是来自荷兰的奥利弗
And I'm gonna say this is one of the more bizarre stories
而我想说这是一个更奇怪的故事
about how the person that bid 28 million dollars to be on that flight with Jeff Bezos
关于那个出价2800万美元与杰夫·贝佐斯一起飞行的人是如何决定的
basically decided they had a scheduling conflict.
基本上判断他们有一个日程安排的冲突
The money was still spent.
(但是)这笔钱还是被花掉了
The money actually has been donated to all sorts of deserving aerospace non-profit organizations
这笔钱实际上已经被捐给了各种有价值的航空航天的非营利组织
so it's great.
那么这很好
That's going out there.
这钱算是花出去了
I just don't know how you have that kind of money to bid on a short flight
我只是不知道你怎么会有那么多钱来拍下一个短途飞行
and then you realize that you have to have your hair done or something else
然后却意识到你必须做头发或者其他的事情
like what kind of scheduling conflict.
这得是什么样的时间安排冲突(才能做出这样的决定)
But seriously this other kid he gets to fly.
但说真的 另一个人 也就是这个孩子得到了飞行机会
I say he's a kid.
我说他是个孩子
He's 18 years old.
(实际上)他已经18岁了
And he seems to be a huge fan of aerospace wants to do it at college
而且他似乎是一个狂热的航空航天爱好者 他想在大学里做这个专业的事情
and more power to him.
这对他来说更有吸引力
Obviously his flight was paid for by his father who's a hedge fund manager
显然 他的飞行费用是由他父亲支付的 他父亲是一个对冲基金经理
but I really hope that Oliver goes on and becomes his own person and does amazing things
但我真的希望奥利弗继续下去 独立 并做出惊人的事情
but yes the flight went off on schedule pretty much did exactly what New Shepard does every time
但是 是的 这次飞行按计划进行 几乎和新谢泼德每次做的一样
because it's completely automated.
因为它是完全自动化的
The only real difference was that we had four people on board
唯一真正的区别是 我们有四个人在火箭上
and we had somebody on the ground communicating with the crew as they ascended and into space.
而在上升段 地面上会有人与乘员沟通
So we got live audio.
那么我们听到了音频直播
We didn't get live video
并没有看到视频直播
but we did get to see what they got up to in space for their very short trip
但我们确实看到了他们在太空中非常短暂的旅程中的情况
and it was kind of predictable.
而这是意料之中的
There's only so much room to move around.
可以移动的空间只有这么多
You can't really fly around like superman
你不能真的像超人一样飞来飞去
but sure you can sort of swing and try to do somersaults
但你当然可以前后摇摆 尝试翻筋斗
and hug your buddies and zero g and throw ping pong balls and skittles around.
拥抱你的伙伴以及零重力 到处扔小球
The funny thing is like it's very clear they had to keep switching camera views
有趣的是 很明显 他们必须不断地切换摄像机视角
because people would just stick their feet in the cameras.
因为人们会把他们的脚伸进摄像机
There was very limited amount of visibility and motion in this whole thing.
在这整个过程中 能见度和运动量都非常有限
It's kind of the truth with such a small spacecraft and such little time to do it.
事实是 航天器如此之小 而时间如此之短
It's also interesting to note the whole thing is rotating as it goes up
同样有趣的是 当它上升时 整个东西都在旋转
and I think there's actually a technical reason for this
而我认为这实际上有一个技术上的原因
because you've got these people bumping around inside it
因为里面的人在这样撞来撞去
you want to actually keep the things stable
实际上你想保持航天器的稳定
so giving a small slow spin make sure that the people can still appreciate some level of zero G
所以进行慢速的旋转 可以确保人们仍可以感受到某种程度的零重力
and the capsule won't accidentally be given some sort of tumble
而载人舱也不会意外地出现某种翻滚的情况
although it's supposed to be aerodynamically stable
尽管它在空气动力学上应该是稳定的
you still don't want it oscillating and wobbling as it hits the atmosphere.
你仍然不希望它在进入大气层时出现振荡和摇摆
I don't think I would pay 28 million dollars for this experience
我不认为我会为这种体验支付2800万美金
and frankly I don't have that much money
而且坦率地说 我没有那么多钱
but apparently Blue Origin have made over a hundred million dollars already in bookings for flying on this.
但显然 蓝色起源靠这个航天器的发射 已经赚取了超过1亿美元的预订费
I'm not sure where the price gets before I get interested
我不知道价格(降)到什么程度 我才会有兴趣
but all the same it does look fun.
但同样 它看起来很有趣
But as a viewer the my favorite part of this flight was
但作为一个观众 我最喜欢的部分是
when on the way back down the capsule hits the atmosphere
在返回的途中 载人舱撞击大气层时
and we get peak deceleration which is like four to five g's.
峰值的减速度达到了差不多4到5倍重力
There's a lot for an average person.
对于一个普通人来说 这是很大的
And we can only hear the audio
而我们只能听到音频
and what do we hear during this
在这期间我们听到了什么
we hear Wally just whipping with joy that she's handling four and a half Gs just like a pro.
我们听到沃利高兴地晃动着 说她在应对4.5个重力时就像个专家
Remember this is somebody that chose to go through a lot of the astronaut tests on her own
请记住 这是一个选择自己去完成很多宇航员测试的人
and she ended up having to make her own G-suit.
而且那时她不得不自己制作重力服
Anyway beyond that we've seen it all before there was a post-flight press conference
总之 除此之外 我们已经看到了这一切 有一个飞行后的新闻发布会
which really was more like an awards ceremony to be honest.
说实话 这真的更像是一个颁奖仪式
The press only got to ask three questions
媒体只问了三个问题
and there was a lot of excited descriptions of the experience from the the passengers.
而乘客们对这次经历有很多兴奋的描述
There was 200 million dollars given to various good causes which was nice
有2亿美元捐给了各种慈善事业 这很好
but after this it's gonna be down to business
但在这之后 就会进入正题了
and I expect there won't be nearly this amount of press attention
而我本来预计不会有这么多的媒体关注
and in fact there will probably be a lot of people
但事实上 可能会有很多人
who paradoxically want to keep a low profile while going this high.
矛盾的是 他们想飞这么高的同时保持低调
They've spent a lot of money on this very unique experience
他们已经花了很多钱在这个非常独特的体验上
and perhaps they don't necessarily want to advertise it.
而也许他们不一定想宣传它
Anyway since we're talking about New Shepherd
无论如何 既然我们在谈论新谢泼德
I expect by now a bunch of you have made some comments on its shape
我想现在你们中的一些人已经对它的形状提出了一些意见
which is yes rather phallic.
是的 相当菲勒斯
Let's just say it looks like a penis
就让我们说出来 它像一个皮纳斯
And I think it's important that we grab hold of this and give it the love and attention that it needs
我认为重要的是 我们要抓住这一点 并给予它所需要的爱和关注
so this is a result of engineering physics right.
那么这是一个工程物理学的结果 对吧
This was design was arrived at
这个设计之所以是这样
because they wanted to perform a certain set of tasks.
是因为他们想执行一系列的任务
So the vehicle first of all is roughly the same width as the Falcon 9
那么 首先 火箭和猎鹰9号的宽度大致相同
because it has to be able to be moved down the street
因为它必须能够在公路上运输
so it's a real road.
那么就得能上路
So it's like 12 feet in diameter.
所以它的直径好像是3.7米(12英尺)
That's the diameter of the capsule.
这(也)是载人舱的直径(解释了宽度的限制)
Now unlike most rockets that are aiming for orbit
那么 不像大多数火箭那样以轨道为目标
this is only aiming for 100 kilometers up
新谢泼德只需瞄准100公里的高度
so that kind of constrains the height and the width based upon the amount of fuel
那么这就限制了推进剂的质量 从而限制了火箭的尺寸(高度和宽度)
so that's why it's kind of this short stubby rocket.
那么这就是为什么它是一种短粗的火箭(但这里主要解释了长度的限制)
But a big part of this look is down to the shape of that capsule on top
但是这个外观的很大一部分是归结于顶部的载人舱的形状
and that capsule was constrained by many requirements.
而那个载人舱受到许多要求的限制
First of all it had to be 12 feet in diameter to fit on roads.
首先 它的直径(最大)必须是3.7米 以适应道路
Secondly they wanted to maximize the internal volume
其次 他们希望最大限度地扩大内部容积(所以使用最大直径)
and it had to be aerodynamically stable in reverse and minimize the drag during ascent.
而且它必须在反方向具有空气动力学稳定性 并在上升过程中尽量减少阻力
Blue Origins studied many different shapes.
蓝色起源研究了许多不同的形状
They considered all their qualities and how they fitted into their engineering requirements
他们考虑了所有的特性 以及它们如何符合工程要求
and this is what was the result of this optimization for peak performance.
而这就是这种优化的结果 是为了达到最佳性能
As I understand it if they'd had a more pointy capsule
据我所知 如果载人舱形状更为尖锐
it would have reduced their aerodynamic stability during descent
会降低在下降过程中的空气动力学稳定性
but I think most of all
但我认为最重要的是
it's the fact that the rocket gets thicker right at the very top
火箭在最顶端变得(比下部箭体)更厚的事实
in almost the exact proportions as well you know what we imagine.
几乎与我们想象中的比例完全一致 你懂的
And this is again all about engineering.
而这又是关于工程设计的
That capsule is defined to be a certain size based upon its aerodynamics
载人舱被空气动力学确定为一定的尺寸
and immediately below that there is an aerodynamic structure
而紧接着下面有一个空气动力学的结构
which is designed to stabilize the vehicle as it's moving in reverse.
它的设计是为了稳定(分离载人舱后)火箭的反向运动
So this needed to be big enough to counteract the aerodynamic forces lower down the rocket
因此 其需要足够大的尺寸 以抵消火箭下方的空气动力
that might cause it to wobble or flip around.
而火箭下方的空气动力可能导致它摇晃或翻转
You'll also notice that it has air brakes and stuff built into this
你还会注意到 (这个环形翼面中)备有阻力板以及其他一些设备
to make it a much more complex aerodynamic structure than you might imagine.
使它成为一个比你想象的要复杂得多的空气动力学结构
Normally during ascent the capsule sits on top of that
通常情况下 在上升过程中 载人舱是坐在上面的
so no air flow through flows through the interior of that
所以没有空气流通过环形翼面的内部
but as soon as as the capsule leaves
但当载人舱离开时
and it's falling in reverse the air can flow through that
而火箭反向向下运动时 空气就会流过它
and that tends to keep it passively stable in the reverse
而这往往会使它在反向飞行中保持被动稳定
总结下，火箭长度的限制是因为推进剂不需要那么多，大约18米，和猎鹰9号二级的16米长度接近
www.spacelaunchreport.com/falcon9ft.html
火箭直径的限制是因为公路运输，以及载人舱要尽可能大，所以是3.7米
但要考虑载人舱下方的环形翼面只在下降段作用，避免在上升段暴露在外部的气流中，
所以助推器主体直径略短于载人舱，给环形翼面安装的空间
while an ascent making it look like a giant wiener.
而在上升过程中 使它看起来像一个巨大的维纳
See the thing is this is all driven by engineering and physics.
问题是 这都是由工程和物理学驱动的
But at some point you have to imagine in a meeting.
但在某些时候 你能想象出这样一个会议场景
Somebody said you do realize what this looks like.
有人说你知道这看起来像什么
And everyone was just sort of but the physics says it has to be this shape.
每个人都差不多这样回应 但物理学说它必须是这个形状
Anyway coming back to my basic theme that this month has been full of long-awaited flights.
总之回到我的基本主题 这个月充满了期待已久的飞行
Virgin Galactic you probably saw that they flew.
维珍银河 你可能已经看到他们的飞行了
It got much more attention in Europe where Richard Branson is a much higher profile.
它在欧洲得到了更多的关注 因为理查德·布兰森在那边高调得多
Again that had been a long time coming.
同样 这也是一个漫长的过程
Originally the X-prize was awarded like in 2003 2004
最初 X大奖是在2003年和2004年颁发的
so it's taken them a long time to get to this spot.
所以他们花了很长时间才走到这一步
And the other long-awaited flight is perhaps the youngest of them all
而另一个期待已久的飞行 也许是这几次发射中拖延最短的一个
and that's Starliner getting its second goal at heading to the space station.
那就是星际客机将第二次前往国际空间站
This has been after 18 months of further testing, refining, fixing all the bugs that they found
在经历了18个月的进一步测试和完善 修复了他们发现的所有问题
and hopefully it's going to work this time
并希望这次能够成功
because it'd be really nice to have two commercial crew capable vehicles.
因为如果有两个商业载人航天器 那就真的很好了
In anticipation or in preparation for this
为了准备这次对接
they had to move the current Dragon 2 crew capsule off of the front docking port
他们得将目前的龙2载人飞船从前面的对接口移开
and around to the zenith docking port the one that points at space
绕到天顶对接口 即指向太空的那个对接口
so that the approach corridor for Starliner will be clear.
以便让出进近通道给星际客机
And while everything else in this video has been delayed by years
虽然这个视频中的其他一切都被推迟了几年
I just want to point out that SpaceX completed a test fire of booster number three with three raptor engines
我只想指出 SpaceX已经完成了带有三个猛禽发动机的三号助推器的试车
and this went through the testing way faster and easier than the Starship test.
而且这比星船的测试更快 更容易
The Starship tests obviously had catastrophic failures.
显然 星船的测试遭遇过灾难性的失败
They had frequent delays.
遭遇了频繁的推迟
But I think it's basically the fact that they've learned their lessons.
但我认为这基本上是说明他们已经吸取了教训
The welding problems have essentially been addressed.
焊接问题基本上已经得到解决
We haven't seen a catastrophic booster failure like we saw with Starship.
我们还没有看到之前在星船上发生过的灾难性故障
And also the ground servicing sequences.
还有地面服务序列
Everything they're really starting to move this a lot faster.
他们真的开始把这一切都加快了
So there may even be a nine engine test according to Elon at some point.
那么 根据马一龙某次的说法 甚至可能会进行9台发动机的点火测试
So obviously I'll be keeping an eye on this down there.
那么很明显 我将密切关注接下来的情况
And I can do it thanks to groups like nasaspaceflight.com.
而这样的持续关注 要感谢像naspaceflight.com这样的团体
So yeah July has been a historic month.
那么 是的 七月是一个历史性的月份
I'm Scott Manley. Fly safe.
我是Scott Manley 切记 注意飞行安全
[Music]
[音乐]